[Music]
button
Professor Dave and Chegg here we've been
discussing galvanic cells from a more
practical standpoint but it will also be
useful to talk about the thermodynamics
behind them so that we can get a more
fundamental understanding of this
phenomenon so let's do that now we know
that a galvanic cell involves a
spontaneous redox reaction generating an
electric current that can be used for
some practical purpose this is because
the flow of electrons which is what an
electric current is can do work just
like water spontaneously flowing
Downstream in a river can do work and
push a water wheel which can then drive
some mechanical function so too can a
spontaneous flow of electrons do work
this electromotive force is defined in
terms of a potential difference between
two points in a circuit measured in
volts kind of like a gravitational
potential difference from a higher
elevation where a river starts and some
point of lower elevation Where the River
Flows to recall that a volt represents a
jewel of work per coulomb of charge
transferred so V equals J over C in the
context of an electrochemical cell we
consider work to be negative when
flowing out of the system such as when a
galvanic cell produces a current cell
potential is related to work and charge
by this equation so we can see that a
negative value for work results in a
positive cell potential which is also
characteristic of a galvanic cell as we
know from learning about the second law
of Thermodynamics some of the work
produced by galvanic cell will always be
lost to the environment rather than
going toward the cell potential the wire
that allows for current flow will
produce heat such that the maximum work
possible is not physically attained
again this is because the entropy of the
universe must increase for any
spontaneous process and this dispersal
of energy in the form of heat is what
produces this increase in the entropy of
the universe
despite the fact that we can never
harvest the maximum work possible from a
galvanic cell we can still make
approximations with the following
equation where work equals the opposite
of charge transferred which is the moles
of electrons transferred times Faraday's
constant times the actual potential
difference
this can also be expressed in terms of
the change in free energy and if we want
to know about the standard free energy
change we simply change the cell
potential to the standard cell potential
with the appropriate superscript this
means that the maximum cell potential is
directly related to the free energy
difference between reactants and
products in the cell for example given
this galvanic cell with copper and iron
and their Associated reduction
potentials what is the standard change
in free energy for the cell well first
we calculate the cell potential which
will be 0.78 volts that goes in the
equation along with Faraday's constant
and also two for moles of electrons
because two electrons are being
transferred for every copper ion doing
the math we get Negative 1.5 times 10 to
the 5 joules
and now we have a better understanding
of how cell potential relates to
electrical work and free energy
Professor Dave for check see you next
time
thank you